# Rajat Prakash Singh Data Scientist

Phone: +91-8800317147Email: rajat199292@outlook.comLocation: Noida, IndiaGitHub: rajat199292LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/rajatprakashsinghKaggle: singhrajat05

## **PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY:**

Data Science, 4+ years of broad-based experience in building data-intensive applications, overcoming complex architectural, and scalability issues in diverse industries, Knowledge in data processing, data mining algorithms, and data predictive modeling with 90% accuracy using scripting language-Python and developing language C#(.NET). Capable of creating, developing, testing, and deploying highly adaptive diverse services to translate business and functional qualifications.

### **EDUCATION**

## **Great Lakes Executive Learning, Gurugram**

May 2021 - May 2022

Post Graduate in Data Science and Business Analytics

### Dr. A.P.J. Abdul Kalam Technical University, Uttar Pradesh

May 2012 - May 2016

Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science

### **SKILLS**

- Technical: Algorithms, Statistics, Data Analysis, Data Visualization, Machine Learning, Quantitative Analysis,
   Predictive Modeling, Modeling (Classification, Regression, K-Nearest Neighbors, Decision Trees, Hypothesis
   Testing, Principal Component Analysis (PCA), Factor Analysis, Cross-Validation)
- Language: Data Structure, C#, Python (Sci-kit Learn, Pandas, Pyspark, NumPy)
- Databases and Tools: MS-SQL, Tableau, Git

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

## Hitachi

## **Associate Signal and Functional Engineer**

April 2019 - Present

- Increased efficiency for application program designer up to 70 % by performing descriptive analysis of error types by segregating errors into 3 groups depending on the centroid values.
- Drive the interaction and designer between the managers to ensure active cooperation in identifying as well as defining analytical needs and generating the insights for business. Inc. 60% change in business.
- Build predictive models using various machine learning tools to predict the possibility of success of project with 80% accuracy.

Tool and Tech-Stack: Machine Learning, Python (Sci-kit Learn, Pandas, NumPy), MS-SQL, MS-excel

## **Ajeevi Technologies**

## **Software Engineer**

May 2018 - March 2019

- Performed individual reports and designed the final and beta dashboards to visualize fleet-related incidents and jobs to meet their requirements. 90% accuracy while performing the ML algorithms.
- Designed and standardized functional enhancements on reporting and analytics utilizing python with ML model and achieved 20% better return in comparison to historical results.
- Developed a **SMART FLEET MANAGEMENT** The module gives measures the fleet km, fleet performance, store purchases, and stock report. Deployed diverse types of Report using C# and SQL with SSRS Report with 100% scabble.

Tool and Tech-Stack: Python, ML, Python (Sci-kit Learn, Pandas, NumPy), MS-SQL, Visual Studio, Tableau

## Caddsoft India Pvt. Ltd.

## **Software Engineer**

Sept 2017 - Dec 2017

- Initiated ML techniques on python to predict the customer most like food as per restaurants from Republiq app data cleaning by merging multiple datasets with 80% accuracy.
- Resolved a Payment module with 4 Different Payment Gateway Integration with all details required for payment gateway, User invite, and Business module with the data-driven dashboard.
- Analyzed the quantitative analysis of sophisticated modelling to address business issues that have improved business by 30%.

Tool and Tech-Stack: ML, Python, MS-SQL, Visual Studio, ASP.NET, POWER BI

## **Ajeevi Technologies**

Software Engineer June 2016 – Aug 2017

• Coded a user-friendly system for Fleet management and different type of stored procedures and implementation of LINQ and provide analysis fleet dashboard and system efficiency inc. by 70%.

• Maintained and test several types of stored procedures for uses dashboard and built API that helps fetching data for apps show 95% accurate GPS data.

Tool and Tech-Stack: Python, MS-SQL, Visual Studio, ASP.NET, POWER BI

## **LICENSES AND CERTIFICATIONS**

- Achieved Certificate in Machine Learning in R by Collabera TACT with 80% marks.
- Achieved MTA in Software Fundamentals C# and MTA in Database Fundamentals with 90% marks.

## **ACHIEVEMENT**

- Selected as Microsoft Student Partner and Microsoft Student Associate among 10k student.
- Selected Best Paper award for "Content based Image retrieval" in 11th National Conference on Next Generation Technologies.